<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-12-19T22:46:04+00:00</updated><id>https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Gang Li Research Lab</title><subtitle>Pioneering AI-enabled predictive maintenance, renewable energy systems, and advanced drivetrain technologies for sustainable infrastructure resilience.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Lab Website Launch</title><link href="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/18/website-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lab Website Launch" /><published>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/18/website-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/18/website-launch.html"><![CDATA[<p>We are excited to announce the launch of the Gang Li Research Lab website! This platform will serve as a hub for sharing our research, publications, and updates with the broader community.</p>

<p>Our lab focuses on developing intelligent systems for sustainable energy infrastructure, combining artificial intelligence, machine learning, and advanced mechanical engineering. Through this website, you can:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Explore our current research projects and publications</li>
  <li>Meet our team of researchers and students</li>
  <li>Learn about opportunities to join or collaborate with us</li>
  <li>Stay updated on our latest achievements and news</li>
</ul>

<p>We look forward to connecting with students, researchers, and industry partners interested in renewable energy, AI applications, and mechanical systems innovation.</p>

<p>Welcome to our digital home!</p>]]></content><author><name>gang-li</name></author><category term="announcement" /><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We are excited to announce the launch of the Gang Li Research Lab website! This platform will serve as a hub for sharing our research, publications, and updates with the broader community.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lab Achieves ‘Triple-Double’ Research Milestone</title><link href="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/15/triple-double-milestone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lab Achieves ‘Triple-Double’ Research Milestone" /><published>2025-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/15/triple-double-milestone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2025/12/15/triple-double-milestone.html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re excited to share that our research group has reached a major milestone that we’re calling our “Triple-Double” achievement - significant growth across funding, students, and research output!</p>

<!-- excerpt start -->
<p>The Gang Li Research Lab at Mississippi State University has achieved remarkable growth in its second year, with major federal funding awards, expanded graduate student team, and breakthrough publications in AI-enabled energy systems.
<!-- excerpt end --></p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-triple-double">What is the Triple-Double?</h2>

<p>In basketball, a triple-double means achieving double digits in three statistical categories in a single game. For our lab, we’ve achieved our own version:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Double-digit funding growth</strong> - Securing over $4M in new grants</li>
  <li><strong>Doubled research team size</strong> - Expanding from 2 to 7+ Ph.D. students</li>
  <li><strong>Double-digit publications</strong> - Publishing 10+ papers in high-impact journals</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="major-funding-achievements">Major Funding Achievements</h2>

<p>This year brought unprecedented funding success:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>NSF NRT Grant ($3M)</strong>: Co-PI on “Smart Agriculture Energy Innovation Network” building workforce for sustainable rural energy communities</li>
  <li><strong>DOE TEAMER Program ($171K)</strong>: PI on reliability analysis of infinitely variable transmissions for tidal energy converters</li>
  <li><strong>NSF EPSCoR Grant ($300K)</strong>: PI on predictive condition monitoring for distributed wind energy using blockchain technology</li>
  <li><strong>NSF PFI-TT Grant ($550K)</strong>: Co-PI on novel IVT technology for tidal current energy harvesting</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="research-team-expansion">Research Team Expansion</h2>

<p>Our team has grown significantly with talented new Ph.D. students:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>William Mayfield</strong> - Working on federated learning frameworks for distributed wind systems</li>
  <li><strong>Youssef En-Nali</strong> - Joining to work on AI-enabled predictive maintenance</li>
  <li><strong>Eli Herrington</strong> - Focusing on renewable energy integration</li>
  <li><strong>Sara Mouafik</strong> - Advancing AI forecasting for energy systems</li>
  <li><strong>Doha Bounaim</strong> - Developing time-series forecasting models</li>
  <li><strong>Obed Kamulegeya</strong> - Contributing to smart infrastructure research</li>
  <li><strong>Zaki Moutassem</strong> - Completing dissertation on physics-informed deep learning</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="research-breakthroughs">Research Breakthroughs</h2>

<p>Our expanded team has produced impressive research output:</p>

<h3 id="ai-powered-energy-forecasting">AI-Powered Energy Forecasting</h3>
<p>Published groundbreaking work on multivariate CNN-Bi-LSTM models for wind-to-hydrogen production forecasting in the <em>International Journal of Hydrogen Energy</em>.</p>

<h3 id="physics-informed-deep-learning">Physics-Informed Deep Learning</h3>
<p>Zaki Moutassem’s research on CNN-LSTM architectures enhanced with physical domain knowledge was featured in <em>Algorithms</em>, advancing predictive maintenance for underground power cables.</p>

<h3 id="federated-learning-for-wind-systems">Federated Learning for Wind Systems</h3>
<p>Developed privacy-preserving frameworks for distributed wind system monitoring, presented at ASME ES2025.</p>

<h3 id="advanced-drivetrain-technologies">Advanced Drivetrain Technologies</h3>
<p>Continued innovation in infinitely variable transmissions, with new analytical models published in <em>Mechanism and Machine Theory</em>.</p>

<h2 id="recognition-and-awards">Recognition and Awards</h2>

<p>This growth has been recognized by the university and broader community:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>2024 Junior Faculty Outstanding Research Award</strong> from MSU College of Engineering</li>
  <li><strong>NSF I-Corps Best Accomplishment Award</strong> for technology commercialization</li>
  <li><strong>DOE EnergyTech UP Faculty Explorer Award</strong> for energy innovation</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="looking-forward">Looking Forward</h2>

<p>With this strong foundation, we’re positioned to make an even greater impact in 2026:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Expanding collaborations with national laboratories and industry partners</li>
  <li>Launching new research initiatives in hydrogen production and storage</li>
  <li>Growing our team with additional talented graduate students</li>
  <li>Advancing technology transfer through our Transfinity IVT commercialization</li>
</ul>

<hr />
<h2 id="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement</h2>

<p>This achievement represents the collective effort of our entire team, funding agencies (NSF, DOE, VentrueWell), our university, and partners. We’re grateful for the support that makes this research possible and excited about the innovations ahead.</p>]]></content><author><name>gang-li</name></author><category term="awards" /><category term="recognition" /><category term="milestone" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We’re excited to share that our research group has reached a major milestone that we’re calling our “Triple-Double” achievement - significant growth across funding, students, and research output!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dr. Li Receives Junior Faculty Outstanding Research Award</title><link href="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2024/04/15/research-award.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dr. Li Receives Junior Faculty Outstanding Research Award" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2024/04/15/research-award</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ganggavinli.github.io/lab-website/2024/04/15/research-award.html"><![CDATA[<p>Dr. Gang Li has been selected to receive the <strong>2024 Junior Faculty Outstanding Research Award</strong> from the James W. Bagley College of Engineering at Mississippi State University. This prestigious award recognizes exceptional research accomplishments by early-career faculty members.</p>

<p>The award acknowledges Dr. Li’s groundbreaking work in AI-enabled predictive maintenance for renewable energy systems and his development of novel transmission technologies for tidal energy converters. His research has attracted significant external funding, including grants from the National Science Foundation and the Department of Energy.</p>

<p>“This recognition reflects the hard work and dedication of our entire research team,” said Dr. Li. “We’re committed to advancing sustainable energy technologies and training the next generation of engineers to address global energy challenges.”</p>

<p>The award will be presented at the College of Engineering’s annual awards ceremony in April 2025.</p>

<p>Congratulations to Dr. Li and the entire research team!</p>]]></content><author><name>gang-li</name></author><category term="awards" /><category term="recognition" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dr. Gang Li has been selected to receive the 2024 Junior Faculty Outstanding Research Award from the James W. Bagley College of Engineering at Mississippi State University. This prestigious award recognizes exceptional research accomplishments by early-career faculty members.]]></summary></entry></feed>